Okay בוקר טוב boker tov today's דף daf is כ"ט Kaf-Tes a
small דף daf and normally when you see this much ר"ן Ran
or commentary you expect that it's going to be extremely difficult. Personally
I don't think this דף daf is nearly as difficult as many
other דפים dappim there's just the ר"ן Ran has a lot to
discuss so let's not be intimidated. So the גמרא Gemara picks up
at the bottom of כ"ח עמוד ב' Kaf-Ches Amud Beis
and we go to the משנה mishna which is dealing with this
idea
of פדיון pidyon and relatedly מעילה meilah although that's not being focused
on with קונמות. konamot. So the משנה mishna says somebody says that
these saplings are קרבן corban or this טלית talit is קרבן. corban.
Now that it says it has פדיון pidyon it could be redeemed
but if you say it's a קרבן corban until they're it's burnt
or they're cut then אין לה פדיון ein la pidyon it cannot
be redeemed. So we'll have to understand why it changes when you
say only קרבן corban for a limited time why there is no
פדיון pidyon but the bigger point to first to lay out of
the foundation which is going to come up later in a position
particularly that of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is is that that קונמות
יש בהן משום מעילה konamot yesh bahen mishum meilah that if something
is קונם konam is אסור זה נדר assur ze neder and particularly
if it uses the word קונם konam we'll discuss later if he
used other words but then it's drawing from the world of קרבנות
corbanot and also particularly if it is forbidden not just to a
particular person but made forbidden to everyone so in that way very
much like a קרבן corban that then it has a lot of
those rules. So number one is there's a concept of מעילה meilah
misuse like when you misuse something that's הקדש hekdesh so you're not
just violating the נדר neder there's actually this concept of מעילה meilah
and number two maybe more bizarrely because you can have a concept
of פדיון pidyon you can transfer the status from one to another
the same way you could redeem something that belongs to הקדש hekdesh
and you
know if you think about a קרבן corban for example right so
פדיון pidyon could work in this sense of of transferring ownership. This
is owned by the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash I redeem it so
therefore I pay them for it and you know in some way
there's that some sense of exchange. But פדיון pidyon can also work
even when it's not about ownership. So for example if you sanctify
an animal as a שלמים shelamim it's not really owned by the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash that's really a question about what its status
is and nevertheless when it gets a blemish you can transfer that
status onto money right onto an object. So this is true here
as well this is not a concept of ownership by the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash but if the thing is forbidden and forbidden to
everybody and it draws on the world of קרבנות corbanot there's a
concept number one of מעילה meilah which we're not discussing and a
concept of פדיון pidyon of transferring that status to something else. So
that is the sort of presumption that we are working with. Again
we are going to understand that the case in the משנה mishna
of קונם konam is not a case of a real קרבן corban
it is a case of a נדר neder which really makes sense
what it's doing here and we are now going to focus on
what this difference is why when you say that it's only a
קונם konam until it's burnt or until it's cut down when you
limit the amount of time why אין לה פדיון ein la pidyon
why there is no concept of פדיון pidyon here. So we pick
up four lines from the bottom five lines from the bottom הרי
נטיעות אלו קרבן harei netiot elu corban so it says if you
say these shoots are קרבן corban etc until they're cut אין להן
פדיון ein lahen pidyon they can't be redeemed. So the גמרא Gemara
says ולעולם ule'olam does this really mean that forever they can't be
redeemed you know like why is it what's this issue going on
here that they could not be able to be redeemed therefore working
within a concept that קונמות konamot have מעילה meilah and קונמות konamot
have פדיון pidyon why is it different in this case. So אמר
בר פדא amar Bar Pada says בר פדא Bar Pada פדאן חוזרת
וקדושות padan chozeret vekadoshot עד שיקצצו ad sheyikatzetsu
yes
you can redeem them but when you redeem them they become resanctified
until they got cut down. נקצצו niktzetsu once these saplings are cut
down פדאן פעם אחת ודיו padan pa'am achat vedayo you redeem them
once and you're done. So what the heck does this mean? It
means the following. You said these saplings are קונם konam עד שיקצצו
ad sheyikatzetsu until they are cut down. Now that can mean one
of two things. I mean you're probably saying really? It seems to
me pretty clear what it means. They're they they have this status
until they're cut and after they're cut they don't have this status
correct? That seems pretty clear what it means. However we are going
to see that בר פדא Bar Pada actually says that's not possible.
It's not possible that something could lose its status
just בכדי bichti for naught just magic it stops being it. As
the גמרא Gemara is going to say if somebody said to a
woman you are my wife for today and tomorrow you're not my
wife that wouldn't work. Let's say you said this animal is an
עולה olah today but tomorrow it's not an עולה. olah. That wouldn't
work. You can't have something meaning I can say you own something
for you know for today you can have a קניין לזמן kinyan
le'zman maybe ownership can be for a period of time but something
that's about something's fundamental identity and status you cannot limit for a
period of time. So if that's true when you said
So what do the words
עד? ad? Says this is what the words mean: עד שיקצץ ad
she'yikatzetz means ongoing. This will remain a קונם konam until they are
cut down. So therefore, if you go ahead and you redeem them
before they're cut down, עד שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz means no, they will
continue to be this status until they get cut down. So if
you redeem them and and make turn, you know, remove that status,
boom, it goes again. Because you know your vow sort of constantly
hovering over it and getting ready for it to reinstall that status,
instill that status until עד שיקצץ. ad she'yikatzetz. Let them continue to
be a קונם עד שיקצץ. konam ad she'yikatzetz That's how he's reading
the statement. So anytime you try to remove it, it happens again.
You remove it, it happens again when you're פודה. podeh. Once you
cut them down and you remove it, then it doesn't happen again
because that ongoing sort of effect is only until they're cut down.
So that's how בר פדא Bar Pada reads it. He reads עד
שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz. because it cannot mean that it stops with its
status when they're cut down, because you can't make something just lose
its status magic automatically. You have to remove it, it can't just
stop. Right, a woman can be my wife, but then I need
a גט. get. Right, something could be a קרבן, korban, but then
I have to redeem it. It doesn't stop being an עולה olah
just because I say it's an עולה olah for today. So this
thing, when I say עד שיקצץ, ad she'yikatzetz because it can't stop
with its status of a קונם konam automatically, עד שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz,
means ongoing it's going to have this status and even if it
gets removed, it will have it again until it gets cut down.
Once it gets cut down, it also doesn't lose it, but at
least the ongoing nature stops. When I redeem it after it gets
cut down, then it doesn't happen again. Okay, and that's how בר
פדא Bar Pada reads the משנה Mishnah and that's why אין להם
פדיון, ein lahem pidyon, meaning פדיון pidyon won't be effective because you've
set up a system, a mechanism where it will constantly become re,
you know, re-קונם-ed, konam yes.
You have a question?
Yeah, once עד שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz and you're פודה, podeh, then that's
final.
Right, right, that will work. Right. So that's how he reads the
משנה, Mishnah, אין להם פדיון. ein lahem pidyon. So let's read that
again. פדאן חוזרות וקודשות, padaan chozrot v'kodshot, פדאן חוזרות וקודשות. padaan chozrot
v'kodshot.
You redeem them and it doesn't work, meaning it works in the
sense that the other object gets their status, sort of like תמורה.
tmurah. You get it on the other object, but you don't remove
it from the first one. So it works that the other object
gets the status, but then boom, this gets its status again. You
try it again, boom, it gets its status again. That's what עד
ad means, ongoing until.
Okay, עד שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz until they're cut. נקצצו, niktzetzu, now once
they're cut they still have that status, but then the ongoing sort
of mechanism stops. פדאן פעם אחת ודיו. padaan pa'am achat v'dayo. Then
you redeem them. That's why אין להם פדיון. ein lahem pidyon. They
do have פדיון, pidyon, but it's not effective until they're cut down.
Okay, and that's all because עד שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz cannot mean its
most natural meaning. That's what בר פדא Bar Pada says. עולא אמר,
Ulla amar, עולא Ulla says כיון שנקצצו שוב אין פודן. keivan she'niktzetzu
shuv ein podan.
No, once they're cut down, you don't have to redeem them. Their
status stops once they're cut down. He reads עד שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz
in the simplest way possible. These are a קונם konam until they're
cut down. Once they're cut down, they stop being a קונם. konam
Now what does עולא Ulla think if you try to redeem them
before they're cut down? The גמרא Gemara doesn't explain and the ר״ן
Ran has two opinions. One opinion is he agrees with בר פדא.
Bar Pada. Until you try to cut them down, until they're cut
down, they constantly get re, you know, re-statused,
re-קונם-ed, konam. I'll just call it that way, re-קונם-ed. konam But then
the other sort of, this is why there's a long discussion, the
other approach of the ר״ן, Ran, which תוספות Tosafot takes for granted,
is no, once עולא Ulla can read the עד שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz
in the natural way, that once they're cut down the קונם konam
status stops, he has no need to read this idea like there's
this ongoing mechanism of constantly, you know, being re-קונם-ing konam it. עד
שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz means it has a status until they're cut, once
it's cut it loses its status. There's no idea that it would
be an ongoing installation of that status. So therefore according to עולא,
Ulla, if you redeem them beforehand, that would be the end of
it. They would be redeemed. End of story. Is that clear? The
whole key is what עד שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz means, right?
Here are your I don't know נטיעות. netiyot. Okay, so you
say
קונם konam
עד שיקצץ ad she'yikatzetz until they're cut down. Okay, so
da-da-da-da-da-da here, now they're יקצצו. yikatzetzu. This is נקצצו. niktzetzu. So what
does this mean? So the עד שיקצץ, ad she'yikatzetz, so basically בר
פדא Bar Pada says, right? בר פדא Bar Pada says that they
can't, at this stage they can't lose their status. they don't automatically
lose their status, there's nothing can automatically lose its status. So what
does עד שיקצצו ad sheyiktzetzu mean? It can't mean that it stops,
the status goes away. עד שיקצצו ad sheyiktzetzu according to him must
be it's ongoing
עד שיקצצו. ad sheyiktzetzu. So therefore you redeem them, they happen again,
right? You try to redeem it, it happens again. עד שיקצצו ad
sheyiktzetzu ongoing. Once it's happened, it's no longer ongoing. Here once you
redeem it, that's my symbol for redeeming it, once you redeem it
then it stops being קדוש. kadosh. Then it becomes, you know, I
don't know, חולין chullin or whatever we'll call it. Or not קדוש,
kadosh, but קונם, konam, okay? But here when you try, I'm going
to I don't know what better word than חולין chullin is, חולין
chullin קונם. konam. חולין chullin קונם. konam. You try to redeem it,
but it's עד שיקצצו ad sheyiktzetzu ongoing. Until they get קצצו, ktzetzu,
the status is going to apply. Here you redeem it and then
you're done. But because עד שיקצצו ad sheyiktzetzu cannot mean that it
magic stops, you can't make the status stop unless you actively remove
it. עולא Ulla disagrees. עולא Ulla says no, once it's נקטצו niktzetzu
says עולא Ulla then they're חולין chullin automatically, you don't need to
redeem it. Okay, because עד ad means they have that status and
then boom, they lose the status. You don't need to do anything.
עד ad means until. So if עד ad means not ongoing, but
if עד ad means until, then presumably he rejects this whole idea,
right? Because because בר פדא Bar Padda had to read עד ad
meaning ongoing, therefore he had this idea that it constantly regained that
status because עד ad meant ongoing. עולא Ulla says עד ad doesn't
mean ongoing, it means until. It has that status static and then
it goes away at this stage. So according to that, if you
removed it here, it would be removed. You'd be done. Okay? You
would be able to remove it and be done with it. It
wouldn't happen again because that just means until, it doesn't mean ongoing.
The other explanation in the ר"ן Ran is that no, עולא Ulla
agrees it means ongoing and it stops automatically. But this is the
easier way of understanding the debate. That בר פדא Bar Padda says
it means ongoing and it constantly regenerates because it can't mean until
because it won't happen automatically and then when you get here you
have to actively remove it. עולא Ulla says it means until so
you don't have to actively remove it here, it stops automatically. And
because it's just a static state here and not an ongoing state,
if you were to remove it, it actually would stop be would
stop being קדוש. kadosh. Yes.
Is this נפקא מינה nafka mina of the position of חוזרת וקודשת
חוזרת וקודשת? chozeret vekodeshet chozeret vekodeshet? Is this נפקא מינה? nafka mina?
This remains אסור assur the entire time and anything you transferred it
to also remain also becomes אסור. assur.
But you know what I mean, what I mean is what's the
נפקא מינה nafka mina between conceptualizing it that way and simply saying
there's no קדושת וחוזרת, kodeshet vechozeret, it's just in other words the
status is to be because
it A, it explains why doesn't it work? It doesn't work because
why shouldn't it work? So the answer is it does work, but
because you said ongoing, it as soon as it worked it got
reversed. Okay? If you just said it didn't work, we would say
why doesn't it work? Why doesn't פדיון pidyon work? So the answer
is פדיון pidyon does work, but you set up a system that
as soon as you're פודה podeh the thing becomes the thing gets
its status again. And because פדיון pidyon does fundamentally work, the thing
you were פודה podeh on also gets the status. So saying this
mechanism is a big difference than saying it fundamentally doesn't work.
So is there a millimicro-nanosecond? No.
It's instant no no instantaneous. I don't know what... Before פדיון? pidyon?
עולא Ulla does not he no, it happens automatically. Because עד ad
means until, it automatically ends over here.
That's the difference between the two choices.
Yes. Well there's both of these differences. Right, for himself to acquire
פדיון. pidyon. Exactly. בר פדא Bar Padda says it needs פדיון, pidyon,
עולא Ulla says it doesn't. בר פדא Bar Padda says it if
you try to remove it gets sort of transferred but then it
reinstills it retakes effect and עולא Ulla says no, if you were
to remove it you'd be done. So according to עולא, Ulla, according
to this read of עולא, Ulla, אין להם פדיון ein lahem pidyon
is not so clear. אין להם פדיון ein lahem pidyon what do
you mean אין להם פדיון? ein lahem pidyon? During this period it's
יש לה פדיון, yesh la pidyon, right, you can redeem it. So
אין להם פדיון ein lahem pidyon really means you don't have to
be פודה podeh it. That once you get to this stage, it
stops and you don't have to be פודה. podeh. Right, right. So
that's and that is the debate. Now there is a so let's
take a look at the גמרא Gemara because now the גמרא Gemara
spells out what's pushing בר פדא Bar Padda because עולא's Ulla read
is a much more natural explanation of what would happen. So אמר
ליה רב המנונא. amar lei Rav Hamnuna. So רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna
said this is בר פדא. Bar Padda.
So קדושה שבהן להיכן הלכה? kedusha shebahen lehachan halcha? Where according to
עולא Ulla did the קדושה? kedusha? Notice the phrase the קדושה, kedusha,
right? So again where because we're talking in the world of קונמות
konamot where it draws on קרבן, korban, we're using idea of פדיון,
pidyon, so we're using these concepts of קדושה. kedusha. Again assuming we
are talking about a קונם konam and not about a real הקדש.
hekdesh. So קדושה שבהן להיכן הלכה? kedusha shebahen lehachan halcha? How did
that just disappear according to עולא? Ulla? ומה אילו אמר u-ma ilu
amar if a person said לאשה le-ishah היום את אשתי ולמחר אי
את אשתי, hayom at ishti u-lemachar ee at ishti, today you're my
wife and tomorrow you're not my wife, מי נפקא בלא גט? mi
nafka belo get? Would she get would she become not married without
a גט? get? Of course you need a גט, get, you need
to actively remove something that's about a status. So here too if
something is קדוש, kadosh, if we were to look at the world
of קדושה, kedusha, something doesn't stop doing that without an act of
פדיון. pidyon. So אמר ליה amar lei רבא, Rava, so רבא Rava
says, מי קא מדמית mi ka medamis קדושת דמים kedushas damim לקדושת
הגוף? l'kedushas haguf? How could you compare ownership of like of value
to sanctity of value to sanctity of the essence of the גוף,
guf, meaning something that is about status, the basic difference is as
opposed to something that is about ownership. קדושת דמים פקעה בכדי, kedushas
damim paka b'chedi, קדושת הגוף לא פקעה בכדי. kedushas haguf lo paka
b'chedi. Something that is about about value goes away with naught, something
that is about the essence itself, the thing itself does not go
away with naught. So what does that mean? It means that the
following. Here's something I can do to you. I can say I
am selling you my computer, you own my computer for a week.
Okay, there's a concept of something of קנין לזמן, kinyan l'zman, owning
something for a time. So קדושת דמים kedushas damim is like let's
say I said to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, I am transferring
my car, I'm giving my car over to the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, say I know that they need to do some travel or
whatever, I'm giving them my car for the week. Okay, so would
it then like stop at the end of the week? If it's
fundamentally based on ownership, right, even if there is a status about
it becomes קדוש, kadosh, it's a קדושה kedusha that derives from ownership,
so therefore that is something that fundamentally you could limit. But something
that is about identity, what is a clear example of of a
קדושה kedusha that's about identity and not about ownership?
קרבן. korban. So if I say this is an עולה olah today,
it can't stop being an עולה olah tomorrow. That's something that is
about something fundamental status and identity. You need something active to change
a status, right, you can't fundamentally limit if it's all about who
you are, what your identity is, you know that can't be that
doesn't make sense that that's like on a clock. There needs to
be something that fundamentally changes identity as opposed to a concept of
ownership. So therefore says he, the idea that this woman is my
wife, that's a status issue. She can't that can't be on a
clock, you're my wife until this time and then you stop. There
has to be some event, some thing that makes it that changes
that reality. I give her a גט, get, I die, whatever, okay,
or a ritual or something like I die or something, something that
fundamentally changes in the circumstances that changes the status, not just because
I have set some clock on it. Okay, so therefore he says,
so you can, so therefore the answer seems to be, now here's
the interesting question, what do I think the story is about קונמות?
konamos? Are קונמות konamos a קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf or קדושת דמים?
kedushas damim? So if you ask me logically, it's not about ownership,
who owns, right, who owns these shoots, this טלית, tallis, it's not
about ownership, it's about a status of being אסור, assur, and the
word קונם konam draws on the word קרבן, korban, right, which is
a concept that is more that's about status, not about בדק הבית,
bedek habayis, maybe that would be a word like חרם. cherem. So
logically I would have put קונמות konamos more into the status category.
But nevertheless, right, it's all just drawing on that world, it's not
really a קרבן. korban. And number two is when I'm talking about
these saplings or this טלית, tallis, right, it does it's not a
real קרבן. korban. I'm not going to be מקריב makriv these saplings
in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right. If I were to really
be מקדיש makdish these saplings,
if I said נטיעות אלו עולה, netiot elu olah, טלית זה שלמים,
tallis zeh shlamim, right, it wouldn't be a שלמים shlamim or an
עולה, olah, what it would mean is I'd have to take its
value and use its value to go ahead and buy an עולה
olah and buy your שלמים. shlamim. So since I'm talking about these
objects, it's a little bizarre because conceptually it really is about status
and not value. But because these are things that never themselves are
used in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you know, as a קרבן,
korban, it's being put in this world of קדושת דמים. kedushas damim.
So the answer is that בר פדא Bar Pada says, בר פדא
Bar Pada rejects that. He says he says no, you cannot automatically
change the status and therefore this has to be ongoing once you
hit this thing it doesn't go away. And and then basically who
was it רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna saying, yeah בר פדא's Bar Pada
got a good point, עולא, Ulla, how does the status just magically
disappear? And his answer is the status magically disappears because I consider
this to be like קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. To be a type
of a status that is not so fundamental core to something's identity.
And if it's not a status that is core to the object's
identity, you can limit it in time. So saying an animal is
a קרבן korban or this woman is my wife becomes a core
identity issue and that you cannot put on a clock. But something
like this טלית tallis is a קונם konam that is not a
core identity issue, that's a קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, and that can
be put on a clock. And that's how come it can change
at this point. Okay Charlie you've been waiting to say something.
Yeah two things. There are times when time can cause a status
of a קרבן korban to change.
Yeah like what?
Such as a פסח pesach when
it
gets too old or after.
Yeah but that's only
when... Also that's not just time; that's because now it's actually a
different type of a thing. That's not a... you know what I
mean? With the passage of time, this became something different. It wasn't
just an arbitrary clock. Right now it's not בן שנה, ben shanah,
it's not בן שנתו.
ben shenato.
Well, yeah, but not just that. It's not... it's not after ten
days, it's when the actual animal becomes a one-year-old animal. So it's
actually a change of the thing itself, right? It's not just like
imagine like you had like, I don't know, some fruit that blossomed.
You wouldn't say what changes its status is time; what changes its
status is that it's blossomed, it changed. You know? So it's... I
would say that that's really not about time per se; it really
is about the thing. Yeah.
But I would segue, in this coming week's הפטרה, haftorah, we have
יפתח Yiftach declaring something to be an עולה olah that can't be
מותר. mutar.
Right, right, so we've discussed יפתח Yiftach again in his time, yes.
I would have thought that a קרבן korban
was a matter of ownership in the sense that you have מעילה,
me'ilah, which is a concept of theft.
No. So מעילה... me'ilah... so again, same way you have a מעילה
me'ilah by נדרים. nedarim. מעילה, me'ilah, there are two concepts of מעילה:
me'ilah: one is a theft concept and the other is a trespass
and a misuse concept. And although there's a famous רב חיים Reb
Chaim that tries to make all מעילה me'ilah about theft, the actual
more פשט pshat is that all מעילה me'ilah is an aspect of
trespass, of misuse, and theft is a form of trespass. Okay? But
certainly מעילה me'ilah in the context of קונמות, konamot, of נדרים, nedarim,
is not about theft. Who are you stealing from? It's about misuse.
And if you think about it, right? If I've got a שלמים
shelamim and I sanctify it, it's still my animal, it's just my
animal that now I have to bring as a קרבן. korban. Okay?
That is the difference: קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf.
So basically what you have here is a fascinating issue: can you
say this is a קונם konam until a particular time? בר פדא
Bar Padda says no, you cannot set a clock to that; if
that's its identity, then that's got to remain its identity unless you
actively remove it. And עולא Ulla says you can set a time.
And the explanation, and as I said, the גמרא Gemara frames it
as קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. What that means in the context of
קונם konam is, I would say, that it's something that relates to...
it is a status of the object, but it's not an identity
of the object. Something that really goes to an identity issue, that
cannot be put on a clock. This is a status, but it
could be a time-bound type of a status, okay? And therefore it
can change, you know, and you can put it on a clock
according to עולא. Ulla. Now, the ר"ן Ran says, "I don't get
this גמרא. Gemara. I don't get why the גמרא Gemara assumes that
it's like... it can't believe that you could make this thing go
away automatically." The ר"ן Ran says, "What are you talking about? There
are all these types of נדרים nedarim that you say this is
a נדר neder until this particular time. All of a sudden, the
גמרא Gemara wakes up and realizes that there's a נדר neder on
a clock? It happens all the time!" Right? Remember the גמרא Gemara
before that said קונם, konam, you know, "you can't be נהנה ne'heneh
from this until... until פסח," Pesach, right? And that works. So why
is it different than any of this? Okay, so let's see what
the ר"ן's Ran answer is. This is important to realize that not
all נדרים nedarim fall into this קונם konam הקדש hekdesh פדיון pidyon
type of a category. So if you look at the ר"ן, Ran,
he says like this, he says...
so it
says the line that says the word דבקונמות, de-bekonamot, it is one,
two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine lines down in the
wide
lines, the widest lines on כ"ט עמוד א'. kaf tet amud aleph.
Yeah, the widest lines.
דבקונמות, de-bekonamot, people see
that first word?
Yeah. So he says like this: ואי דבקונמות עסקינן היכי סלקא דעתך
דקונם לא
פקע בכדי
Ve-ee de-bekonamot askinan
heichi salka da'atach de-konam lo paka bikhdei
how could you think that קונם konam doesn't just, you know, can't
just stop based on a clock והתנן בפרק הנודר מן הירק שאני
נהנית לך עד הפסח אם תלכי לבית אביך עד החג החג, Ve-hatnan
be-perek ha-noder min ha-yerek she-ani nehenet lekha ad ha-Pesach im telkhi le-veit
avikh ad ha-Chag ha-Chag,
that you should, you know, you should be אסור assur until פסח,
Pesach, if you go to your father by סוכות Succos time. הכא
לפני הפסח אסורה בהנאה עד הפסח. Hacha lifnei ha-Pesach asurah be-hana'ah ad
ha-Pesach.
So it says it, the... it applies the קונם, konam, the איסור
issur applies until פסח. Pesach. You put it on a clock; you
said, "until פסח." Pesach. אלמא דלאחר פסח פקע איסורא ממילא Alma de-le'achar
Pesach paka issura mimmeila after פסח Pesach it automatically goes away. כך
הקשה רב יונה ז"ל Kach hiksha Rav Yona zal ותירץ, ve-tiraitz, and
he answered, דהני מילי בקונם פרטי כי התם de-hanei meilei be-konam prati
ki hatam
that's when it's a personal one שאינו חל אלא על אשתו, she-eino
chal ella al ishto, that you say for your wife, "you are
forbidden." When it's personal for a particular person, that's more the world
of a standard נדר, neder, that's less the world of קונם konam
slash קרבן, korban, okay? ומשום הכי קליש איסורא ופקע בכדי u-mishum hachi
kalish issura u-paka bikhdei therefore it goes off automatically. אבל קונם כללי,
aval konam klali, a general one, כי הא דמתניתין דנטיעות הללו אסור
להו לכולי עלמא, ki ha de-matnitin de-netiot halalu assur le-hu le-kholei alma,
that it's forbidden to everyone. כי היכי דעיילן דתפיס פדיונם כהקדש ki
heichi de-ailan de-tafis pidyonam ke-hekdesh
once it's become אסור assur to everybody, you use the word קונם,
konam, it's אסור assur to everybody, that sounds a lot like a
real קרבן korban because it's so much like a קרבן, korban, it's
everybody and the idea of קונם, konam, נפקא מינה nafka mina number
one is you could be פודה podeh it like you פודה podeh
קרבנות, korbanot, okay? דתפיס פדיונם כהקדש de-tafis pidyonam ke-hekdesh כדאמר רב מאיר
לקמן, ke-d'amar Rav Meir le-kaman, אין בין המודר, ein bein ha-mudar, הכי
נמי סבירא לן hachi nami sevira lan דחמיר ולא פקע בכדי. de-chamir
ve-lo paka bichdi.
He also assumes, at least בר פדא Bar Padda assumes that it
doesn't just go off automatically. So the point is, right, this is
an amazing גמרא. Gemara. We are now, נדר neder has now catapulted
us into this world of קרבנות. korbanot. We're talking about הקדש hekdesh
and פדיון pidyon and מעילה. me'ilah. So the question is, really? All
נדרים nedarim are like this? And the רן Ran says no, not
really all נדרים. nedarim. It's a נדר neder like this where you
use the word קונם konam and you made it on everybody. But
if you only made it for a particular person, you'd be more
in the נדר neder world, you would not really be in this
הקדש, hekdesh, פדיון, pidyon, מעילה me'ilah world. That's a רן? Ran? Well,
he's quoting רבינו יונה. Rabbeinu Yona. Okay. And you have to say
it, because some גמרות Gemoros talk about קונם konam and מעילה me'ilah
and whatever, and other גמרות Gemoros never heard of it. You know,
other גמרות Gemoros like just completely oblivious to all of these types
of issues. So the basic point is not all, only very particular
types of נדרים, nedarim, particularly if you use the word קונם konam
and you make it אסור assur on everyone, starts having this type
of קרבן korban type of a discourse. Okay, so what we're saying
is when you use קונם konam and when it's אסור assur to
everybody, and it's like a קרבן, korban, then we could talk about
פדיון, pidyon, but then we could also say like בר פדא, Bar
Padda, well then it doesn't stop automatically. Other נדרים nedarim maybe, but
not this one. And עולא Ulla says yes, it does stop automatically.
It's like קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, it's not like קדושת הגוף. kedushat
ha-guf. Okay. Now we continue. Okay, now you understand why it's so,
you know, why there's so much רן. Ran. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
אמר ליה אביי,
amar
lei
Abaye, wait, wait, wait,
what's what's the 'alim de-tafis pidyon'?
אלים, alim, strong. Ah, alim.
And he's saying you could actually do פדיון pidyon during the interim
before they get cut down?
You could do what? פדיון? pidyon? Yeah.
And then you would donate that to the...
Well, you wouldn't donate it, it's not really again temple. It would,
I would say it would, no, no, no, because we're not talking
about real הקדש. hekdesh. The thing you were פודה podeh it with
would have the same status of being forbidden, but this thing would
stop being forbidden. Right, if we're talking about פדיון pidyon by קונם,
konam, not by a real הקדש. hekdesh. So if I say קונם
konam this is אסור אכולי עלמא assur a-kulei alma and then I'm
going to be פודה podeh it on this, then this becomes אסור
assur to everybody and this becomes מותר. mutar. But nothing is owned
by the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right? It's like, you know, that's,
okay. Because we're just drawing on that world but we're applying it
in a world of נדרים. nedarim.
But according to עולא, Ulla, if you didn't do the פדיון pidyon
during that period until it was cut down, then it's all just
cancelled. The whole thing.
When it gets cut down, yeah. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי
Abaye now challenges this idea that קדושת הגוף kedushat ha-guf doesn't, can't
be time-bound. He wants to be even more lenient than the, than
עולא, Ulla,
than the גמרא Gemara suggested. קדושת הגוף לא פקע בכדי? kedushat ha-guf
lo paka bichdi? Are you telling me that קדושת הגוף, kedushat ha-guf,
sanctity of the very like essence, doesn't go off automatically? והא תניא,
ve-ha tanya, but it was taught in a ברייתא, braita, שור זה
עולה כל שלשים יום ולאחר שלשים יום שלמים. shor zeh olah kol
shloshim yom u-le'achar shloshim yom shelamim. If you say this ox is
an עולה olah for the first 30 days and after 30 days
it'll become a שלמים, shelamim, okay? כל שלשים יום עולה לאחר שלשים
יום שלמים. kol shloshim yom olah le'achar shloshim yom shelamim. That works.
That's like completely mind-blowing, right? So if I bring this animal as
a קרבן korban within the first 30 days, it's an עולה. olah.
If I bring it as a קרבן korban after
the first 30 days, it's a שלמים.
shelamim. It's a terrible challenge.
It's a terrible challenge, I think it's a great challenge. How's that?
Why?
Because it remains in the world of קדושה. kedusha.
That's true. So it is in the world of קדושה.
kedusha. So it's not, so it is sort of a terrible challenge.
No, I wouldn't say terrible, because
if it's about something's identity, he's reducing its sanctity at the end
of 30. Right, exactly. And of course, all right, all right, I
don't think it's terrible. It is true that it doesn't stop being
a קרבן korban altogether.
Okay, but still, if the idea is
that you can't just change something's identity automatically... Fundamental sanctity. I understand.
I understand. Okay, but yes, it is different. You could have said
that maybe it's different as long as it retains some status in
the general world, even a different status. You could have said that,
but it's still a big חידוש chiddush that something can stop, you
know, one identity of
a קרבן korban and acquire
another קרבן korban identity even as Charlie points out, if it's a
lesser קדושה. kedusha. Right. All right, we're going to get the reverse.
We're going to get the reverse. But yes, it is true you
could have sort of said okay, I can see the point if
it remains in that world. But, you know, still, even that to
me is a big חידוש. chiddush. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. גמרא Gemara says, אמאי קדושת הגוף נינהו? amai kedushat ha-guf
ninhu? Why is this, this is a קדושת הגוף, kedushat ha-guf, it's
the very sort of status of its identity, ופקע בכדי, u-paka bichdi,
and it just goes away? The עולה olah status to be replaced
with a שלמים shelamim status? So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא במאי
עסקינן דאמר לדמי. hacha be-mai askinan de-amar le-damei. You're not really sanctifying
this as an עולה, olah, you're sanctifying it for its value, meaning
what you're going to... Meaning what you're going to do is you're
saying let, meaning and the ראשונים rishonim say the animal has to
have a מום mum because if the animal's unblemished and you say
let it be for the value of an עולה, olah, it gets
an automatic upgrade if the thing itself could be used for an
עולה. olah. But assuming it's got a blemish and it can't be
used for the קרבן korban itself and you say let this be
for the value of an עולה olah or for an עולה, olah,
it means I'm going to use the proceeds of this to buy
an עולה. olah. And therefore since it's not the thing itself, since
it's the proceeds are going to be used, it is not so
much about its very core identity because this itself won't be used
as an עולה olah and therefore that aspect can be changed. So
it's not a קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguph, it's a קדושת דמים. kedushas
damim. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ei hakhi if that's
which is not פשט pshat of the ברייתא braita but okay. אי
הכי ei hakhi if that's true says the גמרא Gemara אימא סיפא
eima seifa look at the end of the ברייתא. braita. If you
reversed it, you said לאחר שלושים יום עולה le'achar shloshim yom olah
after thirty days it will be an עולה olah ומעכשיו שלמים ume'akhshav
shlamim and now it's a שלמים, shlamim, that also works. I mean
we don't have the punchline but the point is that also works.
So you start with a שלמים shlamim and you end with an
עולה olah it also works. Now that's even less of a חידוש
chiddush as Charlie said because then you're going to a higher level
of קדושה, kedusha, that would be something that would be more obvious
you could do. Although it is a different identity point, it still
is a higher level of קדושה. kedusha. So the גמרא Gemara says
אי אמרת בשלמא חדא בקדושת הגוף וחדא בקדושת דמים ei amart bishlama
chada bikdushas haguph vechada bikdushas damim if one of these is talking
about the actual קדושת הגוף kedushas haguph the thing itself as an
עולה olah and שלמים shlamim and the other about קדושת דמים kedushas
damim you use its proceeds, היינו דאיצטריך ליה לתנא למיתני תרתי, hainu
de'itztarikh leh letana lemitni tartei, that's why you needed it to give
me two. Because you gave me two to tell me don't try
to say this is all just talking about קדושת דמים, kedushas damim,
I'm going to give you two cases so it's clear that I'm
talking about all scenarios, even a scenario of קדושת הגוף kedushas haguph
that even that can change. דסלקא דעתך אמינא desalka daitakh amina because
I would have thought to say קדושת הגוף לא פקעה בכדי kedushas
haguph lo pak'a bikhdi that if it's about the very thing itself
being a קרבן korban that won't change automatically or go away. קדושת
דמים פקעה בכדי. kedushas damim pak'a bikhdi. If it's just about its
value, that can go away you know after time or change. אמטו
להכי amtu lehachi because of that תנא תרתי tana tartei it had
to tell me two to make it clear what we're talking about
all cases whether it's קדושת דמים kedushas damim or קדושת הגוף. kedushas
haguph. So that, so because it has two cases, the simple פשט
pshat of that is that we're talking even about קדושת הגוף kedushas
haguph and that shows that even קדושת הגוף kedushas haguph can change.
ואי אמרת אידי ואידי קדושת דמים ve'ei amart aidi ve'aidi kdushas damim
but if both the case whether it's first whether it's שלמים shlamim
and then עולה olah or עולה olah and then שלמים shlamim are
two scenarios of קדושת דמים kedushas damim where it's only the value
and the proceeds, if that's true למה לי למיתני תרתי lama li
lemitni tartei why would you have to say two and especially as
Charlie points out the second case is less of a חידוש. chiddush.
השתא יש לומר מקדושה חמורה לקדושה קלה פקעה. hashta yesh lomar mikdusha
chamura likdusha kala pak'a. The first case is from it can go
from an עולה olah to a שלמים. shlamim. So you've already told
me you can go from an עולה olah to a שלמים, shlamim,
okay. מקדושה קלה לקדושה חמורה mikdusha kala likdusha chamura so from starting
from a שלמים shlamim and then going to an עולה, olah, צריכא
למימר tzrikha lemimar would you have to tell me? Okay so because
the second case is less of a חידוש chiddush it goes from
a שלמים shlamim to an עולה olah gets upgraded. If that's it's
one thing if the second case is there to tell me we're
talking about all cases whether קדושת הגוף kedushas haguph or קדושת דמים.
kedushas damim. But according to you that you want to only have
to talk about קדושת דמים kedushas damim who needed the second case?
So אביי Abaye wants to argue that even by קדושת הגוף kedushas
haguph you can put that on a clock. Now presumably not the
case about marrying a woman for a day, okay. So the ר"ן
Ran discusses that. The ר"ן Ran says you have yes but then
he would divorce then, not that it would actually just be a
קידושין kiddushin for a day. So the ר"ן Ran says even according
to אביי, Abaye, right, אביי Abaye is only sort of limiting this
to something like, you know, to something like קרבנות korbanos and the
world of הקדש hekdesh which can all be done בדיבור bedibbur and
whatever. Anyway, but nobody is arguing about the case of קידושין. kiddushin.
But nevertheless אביי Abaye says at least in the world of קדשים
kodashim and הקדש hekdesh he wants to argue that you actually can
have a status even a קדושת הגוף kedushas haguph just for a
time period, okay, which is a big חידוש. chiddush. And yes, as
Dove correctly says, this case is at least it's transferring from one
קרבן korban to another but it sounds like אביי Abaye would even
be prepared to say you could just stop. It could be an
עולה olah for thirty days and afterwards nothing and you could go
ahead and at least if you get it within the first thirty
days bring it as a קרבן korban and afterwards maybe it's total
חולין chullin or something. So that's a pretty radical position. That's what
אביי Abaye is arguing. One minute. So those that don't want to
say that, that want to say no you can't do that by
a real קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguph, how would they go ahead and
explain the two cases of the ברייתא? braita? So let's take a
look and then we'll take the question. So the גמרא Gemara says
לימא תהוי תיובתא דבר פדא. leima tehvei tiyuvta deBar Pada. So maybe
this already אביי Abaye says at least at the פשט pshat level
this is going so far to say that there's even a קדושת
הגוף kedushas haguph can go off בכדי. bikhdi. Maybe, you know, you'll
say no no it's all קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. Okay, I don't
know, there are two cases, you know, זו ואין צריך לומר זו.
zu ve'ein tzarikh lomar zu. Maybe you can explain this ברייתא braita
as all קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. I אביי Abaye want to say
it's telling you even קדושת הגוף kedushas haguph goes off בכדי. bikhdi.
But minimally, like I want to go even further with the עולא
Ulla approach, but minimally it goes against. בר פדא Bar Padda *Bar
Pada*, it shows you that a status can change automatically, right, isn't,
doesn't it show you that? Yes, everybody with me here, right? So
לימא תיהוי תיובתא דבר פדא *leima tihvei tiyuvta de-Bar Pada*, let it
at least be a challenge on בר פדא Bar Padda, *Bar Pada*.
דאמר לא פקעה קדושה בכדי *de-amar lo paka kedusha bichti*, like I
want to take עולא *Ulla* even further and say even קדושת הגוף
kedushat haguf. *kedushas haguf* can go off בכדי *bichti*. But even if
this thing is talking about קדושת דמים kedushat damim, *kedushas damim*, it
should be a challenge to בר פדא Bar Padda *Bar Pada* because
בר פדא *Bar Pada* says that doesn't go off and this ברייתא
Baraita *Braisa* says it does go off. So how do you explain
it? So רב פפא *Rav Pappa*, רב פפא *Rav Pappa* says to
you, אמר לך בר פדא *amar lach Bar Pada*, בר פדא *Bar
Pada* would say, הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar*, here's how to read the
ברייתא *Braisa*: אם לא אמר מעכשיו שלמים meachshav shlamim. לאחר שלשים יום
l'achar shloshim yom. עולה olah הוי *im lo amar me-achshav shelamim le-achar
shloshim yom olah havei*. Okay, now, so let me actually take a
pause here a minute because we've got two parts of this ברייתא
*Braisa* and we didn't explain the first one according to בר פדא
*Bar Pada* either. So the first ברייתא *Braisa* says if you said,
right, כל שלשים יום shloshim yom, עולה ola. *kol shloshim yom olah*
and then it's a שלמים shlamim. *shelamim*. Okay, so the ברייתא *Braisa*
says that that works. And then the other one said if you
said שלמים shlamim *shelamim*, if you said לאחר שלשים יום l'achar shloshim
yom. עולה *le-achar shloshim yom olah*, לאחר *le-achar* ל *lamed* עולה *olah*
ומעכשיו שלמים shlamim *u-me-achshav shelamim*, and it also worked. Okay? So you
have these two cases in the ברייתא *Braisa*. So it seems like
it is going from one קדושת הגוף *kedushas haguf* to the other
and it seems like it's going even further than עולא *Ulla*. The
way if you want to take a more sort of moderate approach
to עולא *Ulla* and it only works with קדושת דמים kedushat damim
*kedushas damim*, you could say even though it's two cases and you
don't really need two, but nevertheless we're talking about קדושת דמים kedushat
damim *kedushas damim*. You were going to, the value was for an
עולה *olah*, the value was for a שלמים shlamim. *shelamim*, the proceeds
and so on. You could still explain that the status changes, that
it's a status change of קדושת דמים kedushat damim *kedushas damim*, not
of קדושת הגוף *kedushas haguf*. So that's in terms of the עולא
*Ulla*. עולא *Ulla* says yes, status can go off after a period
of time. This ברייתא *Braisa* is a very big support to עולא
*Ulla*. This ברייתא *Braisa* might even suggest even a קדושת הגוף *kedushas
haguf* can go off after time, but minimally a קדושת דמים *kedushas
damim* can change after time. That's how it works for עולא *Ulla*.
How does it work for בר פדא *Bar Pada*? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is focusing on this line, but the first thing is,
well what do you do about the first of the first statement
here? How does the first statement work for בר פדא *Bar Pada*,
right? How does any of it work for בר פדא *Bar Pada*?
Some קדושה *kedusha* is changing automatically. So what the ר"ן Ran *Ran*
says, this isn't in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but what the ר"ן
*Ran* says is, well, this part of the ברייתא *Braisa* we would
have explained, when it says 30 days it's an עולה *olah* and
then a שלמים shlamim. *shelamim*, for בר פדא *Bar Pada* what that
means is that if you redeemed it during 30 days, okay, you
redeemed this thing, it was an עולה *olah*, if you had done
nothing it would have remained an עולה *olah* straight. But if you
redeemed it during 30 days, then at day 30 the שלמים shlamim
*shelamim* status kicks in. You redeemed it like the קציצה *katzitsa*. Yeah,
exactly. Okay, well, redeeming is like the redeeming here, except you didn't
say it'd automatically be a שלמים *shelamim*, the שלמים *shelamim* happens after
30 days. This is day 30. Okay, so therefore, yes, it says
it goes from an עולה *olah* to a שלמים *shelamim*, but that
would mean the way בר פדא *Bar Pada* would explain it, if
you redeemed it. Okay? Now presumably you could have said the same
thing here, שלמים *shelamim* and an עולה *olah*. If you after you
redeem it it then becomes an עולה *olah* after 30 days, but
if we want this to mean something else, what do you do
with this case here according to בר פדא *Bar Pada*, okay, that
שלמים *shelamim* and an עולה *olah*, if it doesn't change automatically, and
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says sort of solves it by a re-read
of the ברייתא *Braisa*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, so
let's read the answer again. לימא תיהוי תיובתא דבר פדא *leima tihvei
tiyuvta de-Bar Pada*, so דאמר לא פקעה קדושה בכדי *de-amar lo paka
kedusha bichti*, רב פפא *Rav Pappa* אמר לך בר פדא *amar lach
Bar Pada*, בר פדא *Bar Pada* would say to you, הכי קאמר
*hachi ka'amar*: אם לא אמר מעכשיו שלמים meachshav shlamim. *im lo amar
me-achshav shelamim*, ואכשיו *v-achshav*, then לאחר שלשים יום עולה הוי *le-achar shloshim
yom olah havei*. No, it says like this, you said לאחר שלשים
יום *le-achar shloshim yom* let it be an עולה *olah*, the ברייתא
*Braisa* said if you say לאחר שלשים יום עולה ומעכשיו שלמים *le-achar
shloshim yom olah u-me-achshav shelamim*, it works. But בר פדא *Bar Pada*
re-reads the ברייתא *Braisa* to say, if you said לאחר שלשים יום
עולה *le-achar shloshim yom olah* and you didn't say מעכשיו שלמים meachshav
shlamim, *me-achshav shelamim*, then it'll become an עולה *olah* לאחר שלשים יום
*le-achar shloshim yom*. If you did say מעכשיו me'achshav. שלמים *me-achshav shelamim*
and you didn't redeem it, then that status of שלמים *shelamim* would
continue, לא פקעה בכדי *lo paka bichti*. Right, this is בר פדא
*Bar Pada*, לא פקעה בכדי *lo paka bichti*. Okay, so if you
said just לאחר שלשים יום עולה *le-achar shloshim yom olah*, that would
work לאחר שלשים יום *le-achar shloshim yom*. If you added מעכשיו me'achshav
שלמים *me-achshav shelamim*, then you're stuck with the שלמים *shelamim* status because
once it has one status, it doesn't go away by itself. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* saying if that's all he's
saying, if he's saying לאחר שלשים יום עולה *le-achar shloshim yom olah*
it works, isn't that obvious that you can sanctify something לאחר שלשים
יום *le-achar shloshim yom*, right? So that's the next point of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So let's take a look. מידי דהוה אהאומר לאשה
התקדשי לי לאחר שלשים יום דמקודשת *midei de-hava a-ha-omer le-isha hiskadshi li
le-achar shloshim yom de-mekudeshes*, like a man can say to a woman
marry me after 30 days that she's married, ואף על פי שנתאכלו
המעות *ve-af al pi she-nisachlu ha-maos*, even if the money that was
given for the קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* is no longer around. Okay, so
basically according to בר פדא *Bar Pada* he re-reads the ברייתא *Braisa*,
things' statuses don't change. Change even קדושת דמים doesn't change, and the
only thing that it's the ברייתא is telling you is you can
sanctify an animal לאחר שלשים יום. Okay, the same way you can
marry a woman לאחר שלשים יום. So the גמרא says פשיטא, pshita,
of course. Okay. Now I want to say, I need to tell
you, okay, well, I guess let's read and then we'll unpack it.
לא צריכא, lo tzricha, you need it דהדר ביה dahadar bei that
I said let this animal be an עולה after thirty days and
then before thirty days were over I changed my mind. Does, am
I still bound by it? Okay, so it says the חידוש chiddush
is that I am bound by it. הניחא, ha nicha, so the
גמרא says that's good למאן דאמר l'man d'amar אינה חוזרת eina chozeret
that if you said something should take effect after thirty days, like
if I marry this woman and I say you should be married
to me after thirty days and she accepts the ring, that can
she change her mind before the thirty days is up. So there's
a debate. So if you say she can't change her mind, then
if I sanctify an animal also for after thirty days, I can't
reverse it. אלא למאן דאמר ela l'man d'amar חוזרת, chozeret, but the
opinion that says that the woman can change her mind before day
thirty, so מאי איכא למימר, mai ika l'meimar, so why would by
the case of sanctifying an animal why would I not be able
to change my mind? So the גמרא says no, אפילו למאן דאמר
afilu l'man d'amar חוזרת, chozeret, this is the חידוש, chiddush, even if
you say that a woman could change her mind, הכא שאני, hacha
shani, here it's different. אמירתו לגבוה כמסירתו להדיוט amira l'gavoa k'mesirato l'hedyot
that giving, my saying something is holy is giving something over to
God with my words is like physically handing something over to another
person. Now, what the heck does all of this mean? Well, let's
sort of start to unpack this. So we'll start I guess with
this last case. So first of all, normally saying my words count
like handing over explains why I don't need an act of קנין
kinyan for הקדש. hekdesh. If I say הרי זה לבדק הבית, harei
zeh l'bedek habayit, okay, then you could come and say what act
of קנין kinyan did בדק הבית bedek habayit do? If I wanted
to say הרי זה harei zeh to Charlie, would you own this
Charlie? You'd need to do a קנין. kinyan. You'd need to do
a קנין. kinyan. I'd need to put it in your property, you
need to pick it up. Saying הרי זה harei zeh to Charlie
doesn't do anything. Right? I need מסירה להדיוט. mesira l'hedyot. I need
to give it over to you physically. You need to take possession
of it. So why when I say הרי זה לבדק הבית harei
zeh l'bedek habayit does it work? Well, that's the principle of אמירתו
לגבוה כמסירתו להדיוט דמי. amira l'gavoa k'mesirato l'hedyot dami. Saying something belongs
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is like the act of physically
transferring it when it comes to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. That's
that principle. Great. All that tells me is I don't need a
מעשה ma'aseh קנין. kinyan. My words count. What does it have to
do with my ability or inability to be חוזר, chozer, right? When
I marry a woman and I say you'll be married after שלשים
יום, she can be חוזרת chozeret even though I gave her, I
can't get my ring off, I gave her here, I said הרי
את מקודשת לי ברקורדר זו לאחר שלשים יום. harei at mekudeshet li
b'recorder zu l'achar shloshim yom. Okay. And I physically give it to
her. She could be חוזרת. chozeret. Okay. If I say הרי זה
לבית המקדש לאחר שלשים יום, harei zeh l'Beit HaMikdash l'achar shloshim yom,
fine, let it be like I gave it to the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. I also gave it to this woman. But the woman
can change her mind before thirty days, so why can't I change
my mind also within thirty days? Just because it's כמסירה k'mesira does
not explain why I can't change my mind. Dov thinks he has
an answer. Not parallel. Yeah. It's not parallel. Why not? Because because
you're making the statement to the woman and she's changing her mind.
You're making the statement to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Right. Who's
changing their mind? הקדוש ברוך הוא? Hakadosh Baruch Hu? The animal? Okay,
but when we say she can change her mind, I can also
change my mind. If I say הרי את מקודשת לי לאחר שלשים
יום harei at mekudeshet li l'achar shloshim yom and I give it
to her, I can also change my mind within thirty days. Okay.
It's true. You're right. It's not exactly parallel. I didn't present, that
wasn't the point, but you're right. It's but but I can. So
if I can change my mind within thirty days, why can't I
change my mind here within thirty days either? But you're right. You
need to say that to make it parallel. Right. But if I
can change my mind when I give her this, so even though
my אמירה amira gave this to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, if
it doesn't take a place within thirty days, if it doesn't take
effect, why can't I change my mind? It's exactly different. In the
case of the woman, there's actually a קנין. kinyan. In the case
of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, it's just words. Right. So that
even more that I should be able to change my mind and
but I can't. So the ר"ן says you're right. Logically, it's not
obvious just because you have this principle כמסירה k'mesira but. but what
it's sort of saying is sort of the flip of what Dov
says, because all I had was words, and my words are so
powerful that they are the same as a physical transfer, then they're
even, then they're even more powerful than a physical transfer.
Like, there's just so much power
in that, you know, that if mere words can do it, then
it just shows how powerful that act is, and that therefore it
locks me in and it's as if I said if you want
the, what the parallel would be if it were between people, it
would be like I said מעכשיו. If I say הרי את מקודשת
לי מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום, harei at mekudeshes li me'achshav u'le'achar shloshim
yom, starting now, if it's starting now then there's no backing out.
Okay, so here too when if my, the relationship with הקדש hekdesh
is so powerful that as soon as I give it over it's
like I said מעכשיו and I can't back out. Okay, so that's
חידוש chiddush number one, that when I say לאחר שלושים יום עולה
le'achar shloshim yom olah the חידוש chiddush is that I can't back
out. Now, I want to go back to חידוש chiddush number two,
which the גמרא had said earlier, אפילו נתאכלו המעות, afilu nisachlu hamaos,
which is not maybe as much of a חידוש. chiddush. What does
that mean? If I say to a woman הרי את מקודשת לי
ברקורדר זו לאחר שלושים יום,
harei at mekudeshes li b'recorder zu
le'achar shloshim yom, or let's say, you know, then even if the
recorder no longer exists, she's married. Why? Because if we don't go
through with the קידושין, kiddushin she'll have to pay me back for
it. So in a sense my, the value of that recorder still
resides by her, okay, and she would have to give it back
to me, so the קנין kinyan still, to some degree the קנין
kinyan was the transfer of that object, the transfer of that value,
the קנין kinyan still exists in the world, she still owns, has
that thing and if she doesn't have the physical thing she has
the debt of that thing, she has the value of that thing
by her. That is different than if I said had a שטר
shtar and I wrote הרי את מקודשת לי בשטר זה harei at
mekudeshes li b'shtar zeh and I gave it to her לאחר שלושים
יום le'achar shloshim yom and the שטר shtar got destroyed before thirty
days was up. Okay, there is no remnant of the קנין kinyan
that exists, there's no שטר shtar anymore, right, and since the קנין,
kinyan, the actual thing that he, that was the act that will
create the change of status has no remnant then the קנין kinyan
doesn't take place לאחר שלושים יום. le'achar shloshim yom. So here's another
example: If I said, if I said take this ספר sefer and
be קונה koneh לאחר שלושים יום, le'achar shloshim yom, if on day
thirty the ספר sefer is in your house, it works. If on
day thirty this ספר sefer is like in the middle of the
street, it doesn't work, because when the קנין kinyan is supposed to
take effect after thirty days there has to be some aspect of
that act of קנין kinyan present to give it to allow it
to take effect. So that's why, so that's normal. Now, how come,
so by קידושין kiddushin. אפילו נתאכלו המעות, afilu nisachlu hamaos, even if
the money isn't around it still takes effect because she would have
to give me the money back. Why
by הקדש hekdesh when I say הרי זו עולה לאחר שלושים יום
harei zu olah le'achar shloshim yom does it still work? Where's the
remnant of the קנין? kinyan? Where's the still act of the קנין
kinyan present לאחר שלושים יום? le'achar shloshim yom? So the, the it's
a
trick question, or not
really a trick question, because what's the קנין? kinyan? The act of
the קנין kinyan is nothing physical, it's just words. So because it's
all by words, right, because it's all non-physical, there doesn't have to
be any part of the קנין kinyan present. When the קנין kinyan
is demonstrated through some type of a physical reality, it's in my
possession, I have the שטר, shtar, I have the money or whatever,
that physical reality still has to be present. When it's all done
just by my words, right, then it's all abstract, then it can
take effect לאחר שלושים יום, le'achar shloshim yom, you know, even though
there's nothing remaining of it, I don't have to say the words
again because it really isn't about some physical reality that's being created.
So those are two חידושים chiddushim about לאחר שלושים יום עולה le'achar
shloshim yom olah because transferring something to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
is effected by words, and therefore number one is that makes it
so powerful that you can't back out, and number two it means
there has to be, there doesn't have to be any remnant of
the קנין kinyan because there was no real physical reality of the
קנין kinyan to begin with, so there doesn't have to be any
of the remnant of it for it to take effect. But you
have the, you have the animal, which is a physical object, right?
So נתאכלו המעות, nisachlu hamaos, so they're gone but there was still
a debt, as it were. So here too, let's say the animal
was, let's say the animal's killed. No, no, the animal is the
object that's being possessed, it's not the act of the קנין. kinyan.
נתאכלו המעות nisachlu hamaos is focusing on what defined the act of
the קנין. kinyan. The parallel to that would be is it in
your חצר, chatzer, you know, other types of things that reflect that
act. So it's totally, totally appropriate that conferring
the status of something to גבוה Gavoah is
purely spiritual in the sense that it is only mediated by language.
Right. Well, that is exactly why also it's so powerful, the whole
relationship to קונמות konamos here and this, all this just discussion, and
it's a good point of אמירה לגבוה amira l'Gavoah just once gets
us back to that world where everything here is being done by
speech. Right, it's all these like, you know, it's a, it's a
world of ideas and of speech. I want to make sure I'm
also answering like the most basic idea every נדר neder by definition
has to have some type of קונם konam word or כינוי. kinui.
No, no, no. Now the question that the ר״ן Ran asks at
the beginning of the מסכת Masechet is, so if I said, if
I said, you know, פת זה אסורה עלי, pat ze asura alai,
it's a נדר. neder. Now is it because it's a יד לקונם
yad lekonam and implicitly the word קונם konam is there? Or no,
maybe a נדר neder exists without borrowing the world of קרבנות. korbanot.
It could borrow from the world of קרבנות, korbanot, but it doesn't
have to. So those are two possibilities of whether קונם konam is
always an idea that's present. Yeah, well, it's only been a month,
I don't know why. Okay, anyway. So, anyway, I wanted to say,
I wanted to repeat a point I said before. This idea of
אמירתו לגבוה כמסירתו להדיוט amira to lagavoa kemesira to lahedyot and this
idea: can I back out the קנין? kinyan? Very much puts us
in this world of קנין, kinyan, of like transactions, transferring ownership, right?
Normally if I say, if I say, you know, שה זה עולה,
seh ze ola, that's not transferring ownership. It's about קדושת הגוף. It's
about giving it its identity. But remember, we have said that in
order to make this fit our model, this is talking about קדושת
דמים, that the thing has a מום, mum, is not really going
to be used as a קרבן, korban, it's just that it's given
that value of it to go for the proceeds of it. So
once you're in the קדושת דמים world, you can talk about אמירתו
לגבוה, amira to lagavoa, כל שלושים יום, kol shloshim yom, can you
back out, not back out, you can use those models of transaction,
those transaction types of models, right? Those are more relevant in the
world of קדושת דמים where the הקדש hekdesh idea is rooted more
in an ownership idea than in the status idea. Do you have
any sense like, I know the גמרא might be working or not
working hard to emphasize that it's not about ownership, it's about status
and the comparison is between קדושת אישה kedushat isha and an animal
to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But it's troublesome. You mean because
well, about how we think about קידושין. So let's bracket that till
we get to מסכת קידושין. Masechet Kiddushin. Okay, so now, I want
to just say one more thing here though. I mean, maybe this
will confuse you, but I'll say very quickly. The ר״ן Ran points
out that's the reverse of, you know the joke? The guy, the
joke is after a guy gives a speech, somebody goes up to
the podium and looks at his like note cards and one place
he's got something in on the margin and he's written: argument weak,
speak loudly. So anyway, alright, so the ר״ן Ran says that part
of the חידוש chiddush here by the way, about קדושה לא פקעה
בכדי kedusha lo paka bikedi is that even if you started by
saying, if you remember this second case, you first had לאחר שלושים
יום עולה leachar shloshim yom ola and then you said מעכשיו שלמים.
So he says, here's the חידוש: chiddush: even though you said לאחר
שלושים יום עולה, leachar shloshim yom ola, so this was in place
before you placed the status of the שלמים. And even though the
שלמים status is a weaker status, so these are two good reasons
to think that it could work. Number one is you didn't allow
the שלמים to define. You first put this stopping thing in place,
right? You first already established that you already said at starting at
this point, it's going to be an עולה. That was stage number
one. And then stage number two you said, oh, for the first
thirty days let it be a שלמים. So maybe you're thinking, oh,
that'll really work because I've already got the new status in place
and the new status is even a higher status. So maybe it
can start this way and then get upgraded, and you know, and
I've already sort of put a stopper over here before I introduce
the שלמים. So maybe you would think that even according to בר
פדא that could work. And the גמרא is insisting that no, according
to בר פדא, he is so insistent that a קדושת דמים cannot
change, that even if you set up that whole mechanism in this
type of a way, even that doesn't work. And the only way
according to בר פדא it'll work לאחר שלושים יום עולה leachar shloshim
yom ola is if you didn't say מעכשיו שלמים. But once you
put in the מעכשיו שלמים, it's going to be a שלמים and
that can't change. Okay, we'll end here, yeah. What does he mean
by same law in the area of money not of
גוף? guf?